TLF subtitle
-=THE LAST FANTASY=- 榮譽出品 本字幕僅供學習交流，嚴禁用於商業途徑
by ace_u
-=TLF字幕組=- 聽譯：ace_u aceusub@126.com
(1925) King George V reigns over a quarter of the world¡¯s people.
在1925年，國王喬治五世統治著世界上超過1/4的人口
He asks his second son, the Duke of York,
他要求他的二兒子，約克公爵
to give the closing speech at the Empire Exhibition in Wembley, London.
在倫敦溫布利的英帝國博覽會閉幕式上 發表講話
The King¡¯s Speech
片名《國王的演講》
You're live in two minutes. Your Royal Highness
兩分鐘後會給您直播。殿下
Sir
公爵
Thank you
謝謝
Let the microphone do the work, sir.
相信麥克風自然會引導您講話流暢
I am sure you will be splendid. Just take your time.
您肯定會有出色的表現。您慢慢來
Time to go.
時間到了
Good afternoon.
下午好
This is the BBC National Programme and Empire Services
這堿O英國廣播公司帝國服務的國家頻道 (BBC前身)
taking you to Wembley Stadium for the Closing Ceremony of the Empire Exhibition.
從溫布利運動場，為您直播帝國博覽會閉幕式的盛況
where His Royal Highness the Duke of York
約克公爵殿下…
will read a message from the his father,
將代表他的父親致辭
his Majesty, King George the fifth.
也即國王喬治五世陛下
-58 British Colonies and Dominions have taken part,
此次共有58個英屬領地參加了盛會
making this the largest Exhibition staged anywhere in the world.
這是迄今為止世界上最大規模的展會
Your Majesty, 3 flashes, and steady red means you¡¯re live.
殿下，3次燈閃之後，持續燈亮表示直播開始
Using the new invention of radio
利用最新發明的無線電技術
The Opening Ceremony was the first time his Majesty the King
英屬領地的人們第一次親耳聽到…
addressed his subjects on the wireless.
國王陛下的開幕致辭
At the close of the first Season
博覽會第一階段的閉幕式上
The air to the throne His Royal Highness the Prince Wales made his first broadcast
威爾士王子殿下曾經首次發表了廣播講話
And today, his younger brother his Royal Highness, the Duke of York
今天，他的年輕弟弟，約克公爵殿下
will give his inaugural broadcast to the Nation and the World.
也將要進行首次演講，把聲音傳給大英帝國和全世界
I have received
我奉…
from his Majesty
陛下的…
the¡­the¡­the
國…國…
...the King
國王
(145 Piccadilly, London 1934)
皮卡迪利大街145號。1934年 倫敦
Inhale deep into your lungs, your Royal Highness.
請把煙氣深吸進肺，殿下
Relaxes your larynx, does it not?
這能放鬆您的喉部
Cigarette smoking calms the nerves and gives you confidence.
吸煙能緩解緊張情緒，給您信心
If Your Highness will be so kind as to open your hand...
有請殿下張開手掌
Sterilized.
已經殺菌了
-1,2,3,4,5,6,7
- 1，2，3，4，5，6，7
Now...if I may take the liberty?
現在，我要冒昧的請您…
...insert them into your mouth.
把它們放到嘴
Excuse me, Doctor. What is the purpose of this?
打擾一下，醫生。這樣做的目的是？
It¡¯s the classic approach that cured Demosthenes.
德摩斯梯尼使用這樣的方法治療好了結巴 （古希臘的雄辯家）
That was in Ancient Greece. Has it worked since?
可那是在古希臘，之後還有過案例嗎？
Now if you would be so kind as to read. A wealth of words.
下面，請您大量閱讀詞句
Fight against those marbles Your Royal Highness.
努力克服彈珠的阻力，殿下
Enunciate!
清楚吐字！
A little more concentration your Royal Highness.
您還要再集中精力
I nearly swallowed the bloody things!
害我差點吞掉一個！
Thank you so much, Doctor,
麻煩了，醫生
it¡¯s been most interesting.
您的方法很有…意思
Your Royal Highness
殿下
Insert marbles!
吞彈球！
He can insert his own bloody marbles....!
他怎麼不自己試試！
Tick, tock, tick, tock.
靜一靜…靜一靜
You can¡¯t keep doing this, Bertie.
伯蒂，你不能老是壓不住火氣
I know. Promise me
我知道。你要保證
Promise me: no more.
保證別再找醫生了
Harley Street
哈雷大街
Dr. Chapman, L Logue, Speech Defects
L. 羅格  語言矯正
Australia is calling;Sydney bridge celebrations mar 1932
澳大利亞歡迎您；悉尼大橋留念，1932年3月
Hello. Is anyone there?
你好，有人在嗎？
I¡¯m just in the loo.
我正上廁所
Hello Mrs Johnson, there you are.
約翰遜夫人你好，過來了啊
Sorry I don't have receptionist.I like to keep things simple
抱歉我這兒沒接待員，我喜歡凡事從簡
¡°Poor and content is rich and rich enough¡±
「人能安貧就是富」
For?
嗯？
Shakespeare. How are you?
出自莎士比亞。您好
How do you do
您好
Ahh, traveling alone
啊，就您一個人
Now, this is slightly awkward
這麼說可能有點彆扭…
But I¡¯m afraid you¡¯re late.
不過您遲到了
Yes, I¡¯m afraid I am.
恐怕確實來晚了
Where¡¯s Mr Johnson?
約翰遜先生沒來？
He doesn¡¯t know I¡¯m here.
我過來沒告訴他
That¡¯s not a very promising start.
這麼開始治療，前景不光明啊
No. My husband has seen everyone to no avail. He¡¯s given up hope.
沒錯，我丈夫做過的治療都沒效果，他已經放棄了
He hasn¡¯t seen me.
他還沒找我呢
You¡¯re awfully sure of yourself.
您這麼信心十足
I¡¯m sure of anyone who wants to be cured.
只要他想治好
Of course he wants to be cured.
他當然願意
My husband is required to speak publicly.
公開講話是我丈夫的職責之一
Perhaps he should change jobs.
那他應該換個工作
He can¡¯t.
換不了啊
Indentured servitude?
契約纏身的苦差事？
Something of that nature.Yes
差不多吧
Well we need to have your hubby pop by...
帶你老公來我這兒轉轉吧
Tuesday would be good...
星期二我有空
He can give me his personal details and I¡¯ll make a frank appraisal.
跟我說說詳細情況，徹底瞭解一下病情
And then we can take it from there
然後再做決定
Doctor, forgive me.
對不起，大夫
I do not have a ¡°hubby¡±. We don¡¯t ¡®pop¡¯.
我丈夫不是普通的「老公」，也不隨便「轉轉」
And nor do we never talk about our private lives.
我們也不會談論個人隱私情況
You must come to us.
需要你去拜訪我們才行
Sorry, Mrs J, my game, my turf, my rules.
那抱歉了，夫人，我的地盤，我來做主
You¡¯ll have to talk over with your husband
你必須說服你丈夫過來
And then you can speak to me on the telephone
然後和我電話預約一下
Thank you very much for dropping by.
麻煩你了
Good afternoon
祝下午愉快
And what if my husband were the Duke of York?
要是我丈夫是約克公爵呢？
The Duke of York?
約克公爵？
Yes the Duke of York.
是的，約克公爵
I thought the appointment was for ¡°Johnson¡±?
我記得是「約翰遜」預約的
- Forgive me, your Royal...? - Highness.
- 恕我不敬，尊敬的… - 叫殿下就好
Your Royal Highness.
殿下
Johnson was used during the Great War
這是世界大戰時候用的化名 （第一次世界大戰）
when the Navy didn¡¯t want the enemy to know ¡®he¡¯ was aboard.
海軍不想讓敵人知道公爵身在國外
Am I considered the enemy?
看來我也算敵人嘍？
You will be if you remain un-obliging.
要是你還這麼不近人情的話…
You¡¯ll appreciate the need for absolutely discretion
你對此保密十分重要
Of course.
當然
How did you find me? Your Royal Highness
您是怎麼找到我的？…殿下？
The President of the Society for Speech Therapists
語言矯正學會主席的推薦
Eileen McCleod? She¡¯s a sport.
艾琳·麥康德？她這傢伙…
She warned me your antipodean methods were
她警告我說，你的澳洲方法是…
¡°unorthodox and controversial¡±.
「旁門左道，很有爭議」
I warned her...they were not my favorite words.
我警告她說，這兩個詞我可不愛聽
I can cure your husband.
我能治好您的丈夫
But for my method to work
不過，為了治療有效
I need trust and total equality here in the safety of my consultation room.
我需要在治療室這堣u作，得到真正的信任和平等對待
No exceptions.
不能有例外
Well then, in that case...
如果非要那樣的話…
When can you start?
你能什麼時候開始？
BOVRIL NOURISHES YOU TO RESIST 'FLU
（廣告：保維爾的營養讓你抵抗流感）
Still sounds a bit rough.
車的聲音還是有點不對
You make me drive too slowly, Dad!
是你讓我開得太慢了，爸爸！
Did you pick mum up from Bridge?
去倫敦橋接你媽了？
Yes, I¡¯ve hardly been out of the car all day.
是啊，我這一天就沒下過車
I had a special visitor this afternoon.
下午我有稀客來訪
May I be please leave the table?
我能離開座位了嗎
How special is special?
有多特別？
You must stay, bored stupid,listening to your parents¡¯ inane conversation.
你得一直坐這媔怬b著，聽大人嘮叨完
Thanks, dad!
呵呵，多謝啦
- And mum. - And mum!
- 打聲招呼 - 媽媽我吃完了
- Me too - You're meeting Jean?
- 我也吃完了 - 去找珍妮？
No, someone else
不是她，另一個
Doctor? Doctor? Don't you help you brother with the washing up
小醫生？你不該幫你兄弟刷碗去？
I¡¯m fine
不麻煩了
Who is it Lionel?
萊諾，到底是誰啊？
Why bring it up if you can¡¯t talk about it?
要是不好說，就別提唄
Myrtle, just a woman looking to help her husband.
就是一個想要幫助他老公的女人罷了
And I had a ¡®call¡¯. For an audition
另外，我接到了試鏡的通知嘍
- One of my favourates.- Aren¡¯t they all.
- 我最喜歡的角色 - 就沒你不喜歡的
- Could be a lot of fun ¨C I¡¯m sure you¡¯ll be splendid
- 估計會很有意思 - 你肯定會有精彩表演的
In the amateur scene, they¡¯re a highly regarded group
在業餘表演圈子堙A他們名望很高
From Putney.
從帕特尼過來的
That's all girls.Tomorrow, Chapter 4,The Flight
就這樣，明天繼續第4章-飛行旅程
- I long to know they fly to  - I can¡¯t wait
- 我真想知道他們飛哪兒去了 - 等不及啊
Oh, to fly away!
飛走了！
Weren¡¯t they lucky!
多好啊
Now Papa tell a story!
爸爸也給講個故事！
Could I be a penguin instead?
我還是裝企鵝陪你們玩吧？
Now I want to a penguin story.
我要聽企鵝的故事
Very quickly
來個短的
Once there were two princesses
從前有兩個公主
Princesses Elisabeth, and Princesses Margret
伊麗莎白和瑪格麗特公主
Their papa was a penguin
她們爸爸是個企鵝
This was because he been turned into by a wicked witch
因為一個邪惡的女巫詛咒了他
This was inconvenient for him because he loved
這對他來說可不算方便
to hold his princesses in his arms
因為他想要抱著小公主們
and you can¡¯t do that if you¡¯re a penguin,
可企鵝抱不了
because you have wings like herrings.
因為他的翅膀就像鯡魚一樣
Herrings don¡¯t have wings.
鯡魚沒翅膀啊
Penguins have wings which like the shape of herrings.
是他的翅膀形狀像鯡魚
And what make matters worse she sent him to the South Pole
更糟的是，女巫把他流放到了南極
which is an awfully long walk back if you can¡¯t fly.
要是不能飛的話，回來可是老遠的路
When he reached the water
不過當他跳進水
He dived in, through the depth so fast
潛進去，發現在水堹鉥慦滬葷
that he was in Southampton Waters by lunchtime.
午飯的時間就游到了南安普頓
From there he took the 2.30 to Weybridge, changed at Clapham Junction
先到惠橋那堙A又在克拉彭改了方向
and asked a passing Mallard the way to Buckingham Palace.
還向野鴨打聽了回白金漢宮的路線
He swam up the Thames and out through the plughole,
游過了泰晤士河，從出水口跳了出來
giving the cook mama and Mrs Whittaker quite a shock.
把正做飯的媽媽和惠特剋夫人嚇了一跳
When the girls heard all the commotion
女孩們聽到吵鬧聲
They run to the kitchen where they gave him
就跑到了廚房，她們給他…
a good scrub, a mackerel and a kiss.
擦乾淨，餵吃的，還吻了他
And as they kissed him guess what he turned into?
你們知道吻他的時候，他變成什麼了？
A handsome prince!
一個英俊的王子！
A short-tailed Albatross.
一個短尾巴的信天翁
With wings big enough that he could wrap them both around his two girls together
不過翅膀大到可以把女兒們好好的抱住
Now girls, time for bed. Come on
好了，去睡覺吧
Take the horses to the stable
把小馬牽到馬廄
You have exactly a minute
一分鐘後弄好啊
Good night
晚安
feed them brush them and to bed.
喂草清理後就去睡覺
Will Mrs Simpson be there?
辛普森太太也在嗎？
My brother¡¯s insisting.
我哥哥堅持讓她來
Is he serious?
他是認真的？
About our coming to dinner?
是說請我們吃飯？
No. About her!
不。我是問對她的感情
A married woman? He can¡¯t be.
一個結婚的女人？不太可能
She can. By the way I think I found someone rather interesting.
她倒有可能。對了，我找到個有意思的人選
On Harley Street. A doctor.
在哈雷大街，一個大夫
Out of the question. I¡¯m not having this conversation again.
這絕對不行。我不再和你討論這事兒了
The matter¡¯s settled.
肯定沒戲
His approach seems rather different....
他的治療方法很特別…
Now?
開始？
Now!
開始！
¡°Now is the winter of our discontent
「現在我們嚴冬般的宿怨…」 （莎士比亞戲劇《理查三世》第一場）
Made glorious summer by this sun of York.¡±
給這顆約克的紅日照耀成為夏景
¡°And all the clouds that lour¡¯d upon our house
那籠罩我們王室的愁雲… （理查此番演說表達了嫉妒篡位的野心）
In the deep bosom of the ocean buried.
都埋進了海洋深處。
Now are our brows bound with victorious wreaths;
現在我們額前已經戴上了勝利的花環…
Thank you.
謝謝
Lovely diction, Mr...
試演的不錯，您是…
Logue. Lionel Logue.
羅格，萊諾·羅格
Well, Mr Logue,
好吧，羅格先生
I¡¯m not hearing the cries of a deformed creature yearning to be King.
我沒感受到想當皇帝到心塈嶆悸瘋F魂吶喊
Nor did I realize Richard the Third was King of the Colonies.
也沒感受到理查三世的領袖風範
I do know all the lines.
台詞我都會背
I¡¯ve played the role before.
我以前演過的
- Sydney? - Perth.
- 在悉尼？ - 佩斯市（澳大利亞城市）
- Major theater town, is it? - Enthusiastic.
- 喜歡戲劇的小鎮，是吧？ - 大家都很熱情
- Ah. - I was well reviewed.
- 哦 - 我很受好評的
Yes...well...Lionel,
那…個…萊諾
I think our dramatic society is looking for
我想對於我們劇團來說，您的…
someone slightly younger
…年齡大了點
and a little more regal.
也缺點兒王者風範
You have to shut that one first.
要把最外面的先關上
Close that one first, that
關了第一扇門才行
Where did you find this...physician?
你怎麼找到這個…醫師的？
Classifieds, next to ¡°French model, Shepherd¡¯s Market¡±.
來源保密，線人在謝德集市的法國造型小店旁邊
He comes highly recommended.
這人強力推薦他
Charges substantial fees in order to help the poor.
收費不少，用來幫助窮人
Oh dear, perhaps he¡¯s a Bolshevik?!
哎呀，難不成是個共產分子？
He has no receptionist. He likes to keep things simple.
他沒接待員，說是凡事從簡
The Johnsons.
約翰遜一家來了
You can go in now, ¡°Mr. Johnson¡±.
你能進去了，約翰遜先生
Lionel says...wait here if you wish, Mrs Johnson.
萊諾說，您可以在這媯扔菕A夫人
Or, it being a p-pleasant day,
天氣這…這麼好，也可以…
p-perhaps take a stroll.
…出…出去散步
Was that alright...Lionel?
這樣行麼，萊諾？
Marvellous, Willy
非常好，威利！
You can stay here and wait for your mum.
你可以在這兒等你媽媽
Mrs Johnson. Mr.Johnson, do come in.
約翰遜夫人。先生，請進
Would you like a sweetie
想要吃糖嗎？
He¡¯s a good lad, Willy.
威利這小伙不錯
He could hardly make a sound, you know,
剛開始過來時
when he first came to me.
他都發不出聲來
My boys made those. Good, aren¡¯t they.
我兒子們做的，還不錯吧？
Please, make yourself comfortable.
請隨便坐
I was told not not to sit too close.
我聽說不能坐的太近
when speaking with a prince, one waits for the prince to choose the topic.
還有說話的時候，要讓王子先選擇話題
Waiting for me to¡­ commence a conversation
等著我…才…才開始
one can wait a rather long wait.
那可要等上很久
Do you know any jokes?
那麼就講些笑話？
Timing isn¡¯t my strong suit.
把握節奏…我可不擅長
Cuppa tea?
來杯茶？
No thank you.
不了，謝謝
I think I¡¯ll have one.
我來一杯吧
Aren¡¯t you going to start treating me Dr Logue?
羅格醫生，你不該開始治療了嗎？
Only if you¡¯re interested in being treated.
你真正願意配合了，我才開始
Please, call me Lionel.
叫我萊諾就好
I¡­ I prefer Doctor.
我還是稱呼你醫生吧
I prefer Lionel. What¡¯ll I call you?
我喜歡萊諾這名兒。怎麼稱呼您？
Your Royal Highness, then Sir after that.
尊貴的殿下，然後說公爵
A bit formal for here. I prefer names
太正式了點，還是叫名字吧
Prince Albert Frederick Arthur George?
阿爾伯特·福德塈J·亞瑟·喬治王子？
How about Bertie?
叫伯蒂好麼？
Only my family uses that.
我家人才能這麼說
Perfect. In here, it¡¯s better if we¡¯re equals.
那正好了，在這兒，我們最好是平等關係
If we were equal.. I wouldn¡¯t be here.
和你一樣的話，我就不會來了
I'd be.. at home with my wife and no-one would give a damn.
我陪陪家人就行，沒人管我結巴的事兒
Please don¡¯t do that.
請別這樣
I¡¯m sorry?
怎麼？
I believe sucking smoke into your lungs will kill you.
這樣吸煙就是自己找死
My physicians say it relaxes the throat.
我的醫生說煙能放鬆喉部
They¡¯re idiots.
一群笨蛋
They¡¯ve all been knighted.
他們可是受過爵位的醫生
Makes it official then.
那就是官方的笨蛋了
My ¡¯castle¡¯, my rules.
我的城堡，我來做主
Thank you
麻煩了
What was your earliest memory?
你最早的回憶是什麼？
What an earth do you mean?
什麼亂七八糟的
Your first recollection.
你最先記起的事兒
I¡¯m not¡­
我不是來…
here to discuss personal matters.
…來討論個人隱私的
Why¡¯re you here then?
那您幹什麼來了？
Because I bloody well stammer!
因為我非常的結巴！
You have a bit of a temper.
脾氣很烈嘛
One of my many faults.
我的缺點之一
When did the defect start?
什麼時候開始結巴的？
I¡¯ve always been this way!
我從小就這樣！
I doubt that.
我很懷疑
Don't.. tell me! It's my stammer!
別…別和我爭！是我結巴！
It¡¯s my field. I assure you,
我研究這領域，我保證…
no infant starts to speak with a stammer.
沒有小孩生下來就是結巴的
When did it start?
什麼時候開始的？
Four or five.
四五歲吧
That¡¯s typical.
這很典型
So I¡¯ve been told.
其他人也這麼說
I can¡¯t remember not doing it.
我印象奡N沒有不結巴的時候
I can believe that. Do you hesitate when you think?
這我相信。想事兒的時候會結巴嗎？
Don¡¯t be ridiculous.
別開玩笑了
How about when you talk to yourself?
自言自語的時候呢？
Everyone natters occasionally, Bertie.
每個人都有嘟囔的時候，伯蒂
Stop calling me that!
別這麼叫我！
I¡¯m not going to call you anything else.
我不會叫你其他名字了
Then we shan¡¯t speak!
那咱們談話結束
Are you charging for this, Doctor?
大夫，咨詢也要收錢的吧？
A fortune.
一大筆呢
I¡¯ll just save that brew
茶待會喝
So, when you talk to yourself, do you stammer?
那你自言自語的時候，結巴嗎？
Of course not!
當然不會！
That proves your impediment isn¡¯t a permanent part of you.
這說明你的缺陷不是不可改變的
What do you think was the cause?
你覺得病因是什麼？
I don¡¯t know! I¡­ don¡¯t care!
我怎麼知道！我…我也不關心！
I stammer. And no one can fix it.
我結巴，沒人能治得好
I¡¯ll bet you, you can read flawlessly, right here, right now.
我打賭，你在這兒就能流暢的閱讀
And if I win the bet, I get to ask you more questions.
如果我賭贏了，我要繼續問你些問題
And if I win?
要是我贏？
You don¡¯t have to answer them.
你可以不回答麼
One usually¡­ wagers money.
一般…都是賭錢的
A bob each to keep it sweet? Let¡¯s see your shilling.
賭注一先令，賭個意思？你的錢呢
I don¡¯t¡­ carry money.
我…我…隨身不帶錢
I had a funny feeling you mightn¡¯t.
我就覺得你會這麼說
I¡¯ll stake you. And you can pay me back next time.
我幫你下注，下回還給我就好
If there is a next time.
如果還有下回的話
I haven¡¯t agreed to take you on yet
我也沒確定要繼續治療你
So please stand, and take a look at that, from there
請站起來，讀讀這段，從這
I can¡¯t read this.
這我讀不了
Then you owe me a shilling for not trying.
你試都不試，先輸我一先令了
¡°To.. to..be or not to be,
「生…生…存還是毀滅」 （莎士比亞《哈姆雷特》）
That¡­ is..¡±  damn
「這是……」     見鬼
I haven¡¯t finished yet.
我還沒完呢
I¡¯m going to record your voice
下面我要錄下你的聲音
And then play it back to you on the same machine.
回頭用這台機器重放給你聽
This is brilliant. It¡¯s the latest thing from America :a Silvertone.
這可是來自美國的先進發明，銀嗓牌留聲機
Pop these on?
帶上試試？
There¡¯s a bob in this, mate. You can go home rich!
有賭注哦，回家就能發大財了！
- You¡¯re playing music. - I know.
- 你在放音樂 - 沒錯
How can I hear what I¡¯m saying?!
那我怎麼聽到我說什麼？
Surely a Prince¡¯s brain knows what its mouth is doing?
相信殿下的聰明頭腦會控制自己嘴巴的
You¡¯re not well acquainted with Royal Princes, are you?
看起來你好像不太瞭解王子殿下啊
(to be or not to be.. that is the question)
（生存還是毀滅…這是一個值得考慮的問題）
Hopeless. Hopeless!
我沒救了，沒救了！
You were sublime.
您念得相當好啊
Would I lie to a prince of the realm to win twelve-pence?
我會當著王子的面撒謊嗎？就為了贏12便士？
I¡¯ve no idea what an Australian might do for that sort of money.
我可是猜不到一個澳大利亞人要點英國小錢幹嘛
- let me play it back to you - No.
- 我放給你聽 - 不用了
Alright then, I¡¯ll get to ask you the questions.
那也行，我再問你些問題
Thank you Doctor, I don¡¯t¡­ feel this is for me.
不麻煩了，這個療法…不太適合我
Thank you for your time. Bye
佔用你的時間了，再見
Sir?
公爵？
The recording is free.
錄音是免費的
Please keep it as a souvenir?
您留作紀念吧
No
沒戲
Ah well.
那算了
bugger
這倔脾氣！
King George V.Christmas Broadcast 1934,
（1934年聖誕廣播，國王喬治五世）
For the present(Sandringham House,Norfolk)
眼前的任務… （桑德林姆宮，諾福克市）
the work to which we are all equally bound,
由我們共同承擔
is to arrive at a reasoned tranquility...
努力尋求邊疆的…
...within our borders, to regain prosperity in this time of depression without self-seeking
…充分安定，在蕭條的形勢下重獲國家繁榮
and to carry with us those whom the burden of past years has disheartened or overborne.
不再自私自利，努力幫助那些過去幾年受苦的人們
To all, to each, I wish a Happy Christmas.
我祝你們每一個人，聖誕快樂
God bless you.
上帝保佑你們
And off air
直播結束
Easy when you know how.
知道竅門了就簡單了
Sir?
陛下？
Have a go yourself.
你也試試
Congratulations, Sir.
恭喜您，陛下
Ah, Mr Wood. Splendid fellow.
伍德先生，了不起的年輕人
Chap taught me everything I know:
小伙子告訴我制勝的竅門：
let the microphone do the work.
讓麥克風自然引導自己
Sir.
陛下
Thank you.
謝謝
Sit up, straight back,
坐正了，挺起腰
face boldly up to the bloody thing and stare its quare in the eye,
瞪大眼睛盯著這講稿
as you would any decent Englishman.
就像正派的英國人一樣
Show who¡¯s in command.
給它點顏色看看
Papa I don't¡­think I read this
爸爸，我…我…讀不了這個
This devilish device will change everything if you won¡¯t.
你念不了的話，這邪惡的機器就會毀了你
In the past all a King had to do was look respectable in uniform and not fall off his horse.
以前的國王只需要穩坐在馬背上，表現得體就好
Now we must invade people¡¯s homes and ingratiate ourselves with them.
現在，我們必須去主動迎合大眾的需要
This family has been reduced to those lowest
王室家族的角色改變
beast of all creatures...we¡¯ve become...actors!
我們成為了最卑微的存在…成了演員
we¡¯re not a family, we¡¯re a firm.
我想我們不是一個家族，更像個公司
Yet any moment some of us may be out of work.
沒錯，任何時候都可能有人失業
Your darling brother... and future king
你這活寶哥哥，未來的國王
The only wife he appears interested in is invariably the wife of another!
唯一想娶的女人就是別人的老婆！
He¡¯s broken off with Lady Furness.
他已經和弗內斯女士分手了
And taken up a Mrs Simpson, a woman with two husbands living!
又勾搭上辛普森夫人，她兩個丈夫還都活得好好的！
I told him straight no divorced person can ever be received at court.
我明確警告過他，宮廷不接受離過婚的人
He said she made him sublimely happy.
他說她讓他由衷的開心
I imagined that was because she was sleeping with him.
我覺得這是因為他們睡過覺了吧
¡°I give you my word¡± this is what he said
「我向你保證」他說
¡°I give you my word, we¡¯ve never had immoral relations,¡±
「我保證，我們沒有不道德的行為發生」
Stared square into his father¡¯s eyes...
看著他父親的眼睛，瞪著眼…
and lied.
說瞎話！
When I¡¯m dead that boy will ruin himself, this family,
我過世以後，這小子肯定會毀了自己，毀了家庭
and this nation, within twelve months.
一年之內毀了這個國家
Who¡¯ll pick up the pieces?
誰來收拾爛攤子？
Herr Hitler, intimidating half of Europe,
是希特勒，威脅著半個歐洲
Marshall Stalin the other half?
還是斯大林，威脅另一半的？
Who¡¯ll stand between us, the jackboots,
誰來控制局面？馬靴軍隊？
and the proletarian abyss? You?
無產階級深淵？還是你？
With your older brother shirking his duties,
你的大哥這麼逃避責任
you¡¯re going to have to do a lot more of this.
你以後可不止演講這點困難
Have a go yourself.
努力再試試
Through..the¡­ one of the m-
依靠…最…最
Get it out boy!
說出來！
...m-marvels of m-
…先…進…的
Modern - just take your time
「當代」 ……慢慢來
form your words carefully
腦子想好詞語
Science, I am enabled, this C
…科學，我能…能…
Relax! Just try it!
放鬆！快點說！
...this Christmas Day, to speak to all my p-
…在聖誕節，向我的…
Do it!
給我說！
Lying bastard.
這江湖騙子
- You¡¯re playing music. - I know.
- 你在放音樂 - 沒錯
How can I hear what I¡¯m saying?!
那我怎麼聽到我說什麼？
Surely a Prince¡¯s brain knows what its mouth is doing?
相信殿下的聰明頭腦會控制自己嘴巴的
You¡¯re not well acquainted with Royal Princes, are you?
看起來你好像不太瞭解王子殿下啊
¡°To be, or not to be, - that is the question: -
「生存還是毀滅，這是一個值得考慮的問題」
¡°...whether tis nobler in the mind to suffer
「默然忍受命運…
The slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
暴虐的毒箭
Or to take arms against a sea of troubles,
或是挺身反抗人世的無涯的苦難
And by opposing end them..
通過鬥爭把它們掃清
To die, to sleep no more
死了，睡著了，什麼都完了
And by a sleep to say we end
要是在這一種睡眠之中
The heartache, and the thousand natural shocks
我們心頭的創痛，其他無數血肉之軀…
That flesh is heir to? ¡®tis a consummation¡­¡±
所不能避免的打擊，都可以從此消失…」
Hopeless! Hopeless!
我沒救了，沒救了！
Strictly business. No.. personal nonsense.
只談正事兒，不…不談隱私之類的廢話
I thought I¡¯d made that very clear in our interview.
我不是上次說的很清楚了嗎？
Got the shilling you owe me?
欠我的錢帶來了嗎？
No I haven¡¯t
沒有
Didn¡¯t think so.
別想賴賬
Besides, you¡­tricked me!
而且，你…是用花招騙了我
Physical exercises and tricks are important
身體訓練和花招竅門都很重要
But what you¡¯re asking will only deal with the surface of the problem.
不過你這樣要求，我只能治療病的皮毛
Is that that¡¯s sufficient? Ah, no.
這樣夠嗎？不夠
As far as I see it, my husband has mechanical difficulties with his speech.
就我觀察來看，我丈夫身體確實有說話的障礙
Maybe just deal with that.
先治療這部分好了
I..I¡¯m willing to work hard, Doctor Logue...
我願意努力配合治療，羅格醫生
Lionel.
叫我萊諾
Are you¡­ willing to do your part?
你願意盡力治療嗎？
Alright. You want mechanics?
當然。你要治療身體？
We need to relax your jaw muscles and strengthen your tongue.
我們需要放鬆你下巴的肌肉 加強舌頭的鍛煉
By repeating tongue twisters for example.
通過繞口令之類的練習，比如
¡°I am a thistle-sifter.
「我篩選薊草
I have a sieve of sifted thistles
我有個篩好薊草的篩子
And a sieve of unsifted thistles.
還有個沒篩好薊草的篩子
Because I am a thistle sifter.¡±
因為我要篩薊草」
Fine.
好的
You do have a flabby tummy,
你的肚子軟囊囊的
We¡¯ll need to spend some time strength in your diaphragm.
我們要花時間鍛煉你的胸膈膜
Simple mechanics.
簡單的鍛煉
That is all we ask.
我們就需要這個
And that¡¯s about a shilling¡¯s worth.
得先給我一先令的錢
Forget about the blessed shilling!
別惦記著你走運賭贏的錢了！
Perhaps, upon occasion,
可能…在有些場合
You might be request to assistance¡­
需要你的親自協助
in coping with¡­some minor event.
如果有…演講活動的話
Will that be agreeable?
你同意這樣的安排嗎
Of course.
沒問題
That will be the full extent of your services.
你的職責僅限於此了
Shall I see you next week?
我下周來找你？
I shall see you every day.
我要每天都見你
Feel the loosening of the jaw
感覺到下巴的鬆弛了吧
Good. Little bounces,bounces
好，小跳一下，小跳
Shoulders. shoulders
肩膀，肩膀
Now loose
現在放鬆
Take a nice deep breath, expand the chest
深呼吸，擴張胸部
Put your hands on your ribs
把手放到肋骨上
Deeper, good
深吸氣，好
How do you feel?
有什麼感覺？
Full of hot air.
肺堨R滿熱空氣
Isn¡¯t that what public speaking is all about?
公眾演講不就是這感覺嗎
My wife and I are glad to visit this important¡­
「我和妻子很高興能來到這家重要的…」
Take a good deep breathe, and up come your Royal Highness
深呼吸，提氣。殿下
And slowly exhale and down come your Royal Highness
慢慢吐氣，收回來。殿下
- are you alright, Bertie?  - yes
- 感覺還行，伯蒂？ - 還行
this is actually quite good fun.
其實這挺好玩的
Hmmmmmmmmmmmmmother.
……母親
Short the humming each time
逐漸縮短哼聲的時間
Manufacturing¡­the district¡­
工廠…在這個地區… （「工廠」用到了「母親」的輔音）
- Another deep breath and ¡°jack and Jill¡± - ¡°Jack and Jill¡±
- 再次深吸氣，說「傑克和吉爾」 - 「傑克和吉爾」（兒童歌謠）
- Went up the hill - went up the hill
- 一起上山
Just sway¡­ perfect
搖擺身體…很好
We are not permit to ask¡­to
「我們這樣要求可能過分…」
Loosen the shoulder
放鬆肩膀
Ding dong bell, Pussy¡¯s in the well
叮咚鈴響，小貓掉進井堣F （兒童歌謠）
Who put her in? Little Johnny Green
誰扔的？小約翰·格林
Have a short memory Bertie? Come on
記性不好了，伯蒂？繼續
- cow - cow
- cow（奶牛）
- king - king
- king（國王）
Anyone who can shout vowels in an open window can learn to deliver a speech.
只要能大聲對著窗外喊出元音， 就肯定能開口演講
- 14¡­15 - Deep breath. And it is..
- 14…15秒 - 深呼吸
- it is ... - let the words flow
- 這樣… - 讓詞語脫口而出
mine doesn¡¯t bloody work
我的嘴怎麼不行
come on, one more time, Bertie
加油，再試一次，伯蒂
you can do it
你能行的
a sieve of sifted thistles
一個篩好薊草的篩子
- father - father
- father（父親）
- Wait for ¡°aa¡± in patient - father
- 耐心等待詞中的元音
Sandringham Estate 1936
桑德林姆宮，1936年
- Hello, Bertie. - Hello David
- 你好，伯蒂 - 你好，大衛
- I see you¡¯ve been coming out - Not at all
- 現在常出來玩？ - 沒這習慣
Been waiting long? For Christ, bloody freezing
等了很久？我的天，這麼冷
Where¡¯ve you been?
你去哪兒了？
Been busy.
到處忙
So was I. Elizabeth has pneumonia.
我也是，伊麗莎白得了肺炎
I¡¯m sorry. She¡¯ll recover.
我很難過。不過她會好的
Father won¡¯t.
父親不會
I¡¯ll drive.
我來開車
Old bugger¡¯s doing this on purpose.
老傢伙肯定是有意這麼做的
Dying?
尋死？
Departing prematurely to complicate matters with Wallis.
他這麼做，是有意攪亂我和華莉絲的事
Oh for heaven¡¯s sake, David.
看在老天的份上，大衛
You know how long he¡¯s been ill.
他一直有病，你怎麼這麼想
Wallis explained. She¡¯s terribly clever about these things.
華莉絲解釋給我的，她這方面腦筋很好使
... whereas by letters patent under the Great Seal,
…根據國印證明的文件
bearing date of Westminster, the eleventh June 1912
1912年6月11日，在威斯敏斯特議會大廈
his Majesty King George V did constitute,
國王喬治五世確實任命過…
order and declare that there should be a guardian,
說需要有個監護人的角色
- what¡¯s going on here? - Custos Regni, in the form of Councilors of State.
- 這是怎麼回事？ - 以議會的形式
I cannot follow you. I¡¯m confused and I don¡¯t understand
我完全聽不懂你在說什麼
- ¡­ what you¡¯re taking about  - It¡¯s the order of the Council for the State, Sir.
- 聽不明白 - 是議會的決議，陛下
- would you do that? - So we may act on your behalf.
- 誰幫幫我？ - 我們能代您行使權利
not clearly I¡¯m afraid...I¡¯m still confused...
表達的不清楚，我還是沒懂什麼意思
But Approved. Thank you.
- 您同意就好 - 謝謝
- Let me help you sir - alright
- 我來幫您，陛下 - 好的
- thank you sir - thank you
- 謝謝陛下 - 謝謝
Feeling a little better Sir?
覺得好點了嗎，陛下？
No. I¡¯m not feeling any better. I feel dreadful.
沒有任何好轉，我感覺很糟
Been ice-skating?
你去滑冰玩了？
No, George.
沒有，喬治
Yes, he¡¯s alright. Of course.
他肯定沒事兒
I know, darling, a talk, even a lovely long talk,
我知道，親愛的，這樣長談…
is a poor substitute for holding tight and making drowsy.
也絕比不上和你相擁而眠
Nor making our own drowsies either,
近期見面肯定不容易
as we¡¯ve had to do far too often lately.
尤其是和你一起
- David, the dinner - I¡¯m on with Wallis
- 大衛，吃晚飯了 - 我在和華莉絲通話
It¡¯s Bertie.
是伯蒂
No, it¡¯s not important. No. I don¡¯t want to
不是要緊事兒。…我也不想啊
No, telephone me later? Right, bye
回頭給我電話？好了，再見
Wallis misses me terribly.
華莉絲非常想念我
Mama says you¡¯re late for dinner.
媽媽說你吃晚飯遲到了
She forgets Papa¡¯s bloody clocks were always half an hour fast!
她忘了老爸的表總是撥快半個小時！
How is the king? I hope he is not in pain.
國王身體如何？希望他疼痛緩解
No, no, His Majesty is quieter now.
沒事兒了，陛下現在安靜很多了
Thank you
謝謝
David, if your father were here, tardiness would not be tolerated.
大衛，要是你父親在 這樣不守時是絕不允許的
None of this..unpleasantness would be tolerated
不可能容忍任何這些無禮舉止
You know Sir, I appreciate that you are different from your father
殿下，我很欣賞您和國王有所不同的…
Both in outlook and temperament.
…性格和眼光
I want you to know that whenever the King questioned your conduct,
我希望您明白，每當國王質詢您的舉止時
I tried in your interest to present it in a most favorable light.
我總是說好話，把您的最佳一面展現出來
I can always trust you to have my best interests at heart.
我相信您會把我的利益放在心上
I¡¯m fear our vigil will not be of long duration.
恐怕我們的守夜時間不會長了…
Please continue, thank you
請繼續用餐，謝謝…
just commend our brother George to the mercy of God,
請把我們的兄弟喬治托付給仁慈的上帝
our Maker and Redeemer.
我們的造物主，贖罪者
Long live the King.
國王萬歲
I hope I will make good as he has made good.
但願我能成為父親那樣好國王
What on earth was that?
你剛才究竟是怎麼了？
Poor Wallis. Now I¡¯m trapped!
可憐的華莉絲。我是解脫不了了
And in these last 25 crowded troubled glorious years
在過去的25年的風風雨雨中
If there¡¯s one thing that King George has taught
國王喬治教給了我們最重要的…
It is the art of the leader with also a brother to his followers
是他的領袖風範，以及對臣民兄長般的溫暖
As long as he lives he was the guiding star of a great nation
他活著的時候，是整個帝國的指路明燈
Dad? (When he died, the little children cried in the street)
爸爸？ （廣播：當國王過世，街上的小朋友們失聲痛哭）
Time for a Shake, dad?
換換腦筋？
- You sure? - Go on
- 你願意？ - 來吧
Put your thinking caps on.
你們得絞盡腦汁了
Bet its the Scottish Play.
我猜他要演蘇格蘭戲劇
No, I bet it¡¯s Othello. It¡¯s always Othello.
我猜是《奧賽羅》，每次都是
¡°Art thou afeard? Be not afeard¡±
「您害怕嗎？不要怕」 （莎士比亞戲劇《暴風雨》）
- Caliban! - Oh! For heaven¡¯s sake.. that was a lucky guess!
- 你演的是 凱列班 - 老天爺，你這是碰巧猜中
Don¡¯t listen to egghead. Go on, Dad.
別理書獃子了，爸爸你繼續
¡°the isle is full of noises,
「這島上充滿了各種聲音」 （凱列班是該劇的頭號反派）
Sounds and sweet airs, that give delight, and hurt not.
「悅耳的樂曲，使人聽了愉快，不會傷人」 （《暴風雨》第三幕第三場）
Sometimes a thousand twanging instruments
「有時成千的叮咚樂器…」
Will hum about mine ears; and sometimes voices,
「在我耳邊鳴響；有時醒來聽到歌聲」
That, if then I had waked after long sleep, Will make me sleep again:¡±
「又讓我沉沉睡去」
Alright, clever clogs, what comes next?
那好，攪局的小子，下面什麼台詞？
- ¡°..and then, in dreaming, Me thought the clouds¡± - the clouds me thought
- 「然後在夢中，我在雲端…」 - 是「在雲端，我」
¡°The clouds me thought would open,
「在雲端…我見雲層打開」
And show riches Ready to drop upon me; that...¡±
「無數珍寶向我傾倒下來」
...when I waked, I cried to dream again.¡±
「醒來後，哭著想要再做一遍同樣的夢」
It¡¯s such a sad thought.
真麼想可真可憐
My next patient must be a bit early. You better go lads, I¡¯m sorry.
我下個病人來早了，抱歉你們得先走了
Won¡¯t be a moment, Clifford.
克利福德，你稍等一下
Bertie, they told me not to expect you.
伯蒂，他們通知我你不過來了
Sorry about your father.
對你父親的過世，我很遺憾
I don¡¯t wish to intrude..
我不想冒昧打擾的…
No..Not at all, please come in
不不，沒關係，請進
I¡¯ve been practising. One hour a day.
我一直在練習，每天一小時
In spite of everything.
雷打不動
What¡¯s going on there?
這是怎麼回事？
I was, sorry, mucking around with my kids.
抱歉，我和孩子們鬧著玩著
Do you feel like working today?
今天還想練習一下？
A Curtis bi-plane.
柯蒂斯雙翼飛機
I¡¯ll put on some hot milk.
我準備點熱牛奶
Logue, I¡¯d kill for something stronger.
羅格，給我來點烈酒
I wasn¡¯t there for my father¡¯s death.
我沒見到我父親的最後一面
Still makes me sad.
我心堣@直很過意不去
I can imagine so.
我能理解
- What did you father do?  - He was brewer.
- 你父親是做什麼的？ - 釀酒師
- Oh. - At least there was free beer.
- 噢 - 至少我有免費啤酒
Here¡¯s to the memory of your father.
為紀念你父親，乾一杯
I was informed, after the fact,
在他…過世後，有人告訴我
my father¡¯s ¡­last words were:
我父親的…遺言是：
¡°Bertie has more.. guts than the rest of his brothers.. put together.¡±
「伯蒂比…他所有兄弟加起來…還要勇敢」
He couldn¡¯t say that to my face.
可惜他沒能當面告訴我
My brother.
我哥哥
What about him?
他怎麼了
- Try singing it. - I¡¯m sorry?
- 你可以唱著說 - 什麼？
What songs do you know?
你會唱什麼曲子？
- Songs? - ¡°Swanee River¡±
- 歌謠？ - 《斯旺尼河》
- I love that song. - Happens to be my favorite.
- 我喜歡這曲子 - 正好是我的最愛
- Sing me the chorus. - No. Certainly not.
- 把和聲哼給我聽 - 不，肯定不唱
I always.. wanted to build models.
我一直…想要做模型
Father¡­ wouldn¡¯t allow it. He.. collected stamps.
父親…不會允許的。他…集郵
We had to collect stamps.
我們也得集郵
You can finish that off. If you sing.
要是唱歌的話，你就可以把它做完
- ¡°My brother David, doo-dah¡± - I¡¯m not going to sit here wobbling
- 「我哥哥大衛，啦啦啦」 - 我不會坐在這兒傻唱的
You can with me.
和我別見外
Because¡­ you¡¯re peculiar.
是啊…因為你很怪
I take that as a compliment.
我就把這當成讚美嘍
Rules are rules
你得守規矩
I¡¯m not¡­crooning ¡°Swanee River!¡±
我才不會…哼唱《斯旺尼河》！
Try ¡°Camptown Races¡± then.
那換成《康城賽馬歌》
¡°My brother D, he said to me, doodah doo-dah...¡±
「我哥大衛，他對我說，啦啦啦啦」
- Continuous sound will give you flow. - No
- 連續發聲讓你保持連貫 - 不行
Does it feel strange, now that David¡¯s on the throne?
現在大衛成了國王，你不覺得不舒服嗎？
Tell you the truth, It was a relief...
實話實說，我是鬆了一口氣
Knowing.. I wouldn't be ..King.
得知…國王不是…是我
But unless he produces an heir, you¡¯re next in line.
不過如果他沒有後代，那你就是接班人
And your daughter, Elizabeth, would then succeed you.
然後你女兒伊麗莎白會接替你
¡°You¡¯re barking up the wrong tree now, Doctor, Doctor.¡±
「這個話題可不對頭，醫生，醫生」
¡°Lionel,¡± You didn¡¯t stammer.
叫我「萊諾」，你沒結巴啊
Of course I didn¡¯t stammer, I was singing!
當然不會，我在唱歌！
Well, as a little reward,
好吧，作為小小的獎勵
you get to put some glue on these struts.
你可以在這些支架上塗些膠水
- your boy wouldn¡¯t mind? - No, not at all
- 你兒子不介意吧？ - 不會，放心吧
David and I were very close.
我和大衛很親近
Young bucks... You know.
像兩頭年輕的雄鹿…你懂的
Did you chase the same girls?
追求過同一個女孩？
David was always very helpful in arranging introductions.
大衛牽線搭橋很在行
We shared¡­ the expert ministrations of ¡°Paulette¡± in Paris.
我們享受過…巴黎「波萊特」館的頂級服務
Not at the same time of course.
當然不是同時來了
Did David ever tease you?
大衛取笑過你嗎？
Oh yes they all did.
當然，別人總是這樣
¡°Buh-buh-buh-Bertie¡±.
「伯伯伯…伯蒂」
Father encouraged it.
父親也推波助瀾
¡°Get it out, boy!¡±
「快點說啊，小子」
Said it would make me stop.
以為這樣就能讓我不結巴
Said...¡±I was afraid of my father,
他說，「我就很怕我爸」
and my children are damn well going to be afraid of me¡±.
「我孩子怕我是理所當然」
Are you naturally right handed?
你是天生習慣右手嗎？
Left. I was¡­ punished. Now I use the right.
我以前是左撇子…老罰我，就改成右手了
Yes, that¡¯s very common with stammerers.
這在結巴患者中挺常見的
Anything other corrections?
還有什麼矯正之類的？
Knock knees.
膝蓋外翻
Metal¡­ splints were made...worn¡­day and night
金屬…夾板套著…晝夜都得帶
That must have been painful.
那肯定不好受
Bloody agony. Straight legs now.
非常難受。總算現在是直腿了
Who were you closest to in your family?
家堣H誰和你最親近
Nannies. Not my first nanny..
奶媽。不過不是最早的那個
she loved David...hated me.
她喜歡大衛，討厭我
When I.. was presented to my parents for the daily viewing,
每天我該見父母的時候…
she¡¯d...She pinch me so I¡¯d cry,
她…她都掐我，我就哭
and be¡­handed back to her immediately,
然後我…就馬上帶回來讓她照顧
then she wouldn¡¯t¡­
然後她就不…
- sing it - then she wouldn¡¯t feed me, far far away.¡±
- 唱出來吧 - 她就不讓我吃飯，離我遠遠的
Took my parents three years to notice.
我父母三年以後才發現
As you can imagine,
你也能想像的到
it caused some stomach problems. Still.
給我胃留下了病根，現在還沒好
What about your brother Johnnie?
你兄弟喬尼呢？
Were you close to him?
和他親近嗎？
Johnnie, Sweet boy.
喬尼，人很不錯
Epilepsy...and...he was 'different'.
有癲癇…他…有點「怪」
He died at 13, hidden from view.
13歲死後，家堣H就不再提他
I¡¯ve been told it¡¯s not catching.
大人說這不是光彩事兒
- Do you want a top-up? - Please.
- 再加點酒 - 多謝
You know, Lionel,
其實，萊諾…
- you¡¯re the first ordinary Englishman... - Australian.
- 你是第一個英國平民… - 澳大利亞人
...I¡¯ve ever really spoken to.
…我能親口交談的人
when I¡¯m driven through the streets and see,
以前我坐車路過大街
you know, the Common Man staring at me,
看到百姓們盯著我看
I¡¯m struck by how little I know of his life,
我忽然想到…
and how little he knows of mine.
我們其實都彼此瞭解甚少
- Thank you - What¡¯re friends for.
- 謝謝 - 朋友就是彌補這一點的
I wouldn¡¯t know.
以前我不懂
Balmoral Castle, Scotland
巴爾默羅城堡，蘇格蘭
¡°I sifted seven thick-stalked thistles
「我篩出來七根硬桿薊草」 （順口溜）
through strong thick sieves.
用我又厚又硬的篩子
I sifted seven...¡±
我篩出來七…
- isn¡¯t that enough darling? No? - I have to keep doing this
- 親愛的，你不歇歇嗎？ - 我必須堅持練習才行
This is your fault.
這都怪你
- I sifted seven - Oh no
- 我篩出來七根 - 哦不
One hundred year old spruces removed to improve the view!
一百年的雲杉就這麼砍了，怕擋她視線
Who do you think she is?
她以為她算老幾
Nonetheless...we must try to be pleasant towards Mrs Simpson.
不過…我們必須對辛普森太太表現的友好些
You know she calls me ¡°The Fat Scottish Cook¡±?
你知道她叫我「蘇格蘭的胖廚師」嗎
You¡¯re not fat.
你才不胖
I¡¯m getting plump.
我是有點豐滿了
You seldom cook.
你也不做飯啊
- I sifted seven. - Shut up!!
- 我篩出來七 - 閉嘴啦
I sifted¡­
我篩出來…
- 3,2,1 and booze - Their Royal Highnesses the Duke and Duchess of York.
- 3，2，1，酒會開始 - 約克公爵和公爵夫人殿下到來
How lovely to see you both.
真高興見到你們倆
Welcome to our little country shack.
歡迎來到我們的鄉村小屋
I came at the invitation of the King.
我是應國王的邀請而來
Your Majesty
陛下
- All right - Sorry we¡¯re late
- 好的 - 抱歉我們遲到了
Very nice to see you, Mrs Simpson
見到您很高興，辛普森太太
Very nice
很高興
Hello David.
你好，大衛
Making¡­ some changes to the garden I see.
我看你…改造了…花園
I am. I am not quite finished yet.
是啊，還沒完工
Don¡¯t tell me I behaved badly, Mr Churchill.
我這算舉止無禮嗎，丘吉爾先生？
On the contrary, your Royal Highness.
正好相反，殿下
Etiquette decrees royalty should be greeted by the official host:
禮節規定要由宴會主人接待王室成員
in this case: the King. Not a commoner.
應該是國王本人迎接你，而不是平民百姓
- Thank you. - what is her hold on him?
- 謝謝 - 她怎麼迷住他的？
I¡¯ve no idea.
想不明白啊
Apparently she has certain...skills,
不過顯然她有些…技巧
which she learnt in an establishment in Shanghai.
在上海的圈子練就了一身功夫
- David - just be a sec, darling
- 大衛 - 馬上就弄好，寶貝
Excuse me.
失陪
David, I¡¯ve been trying to see you...
大衛，我一直想要見你
I¡¯ve been terribly busy.
我日理萬機啊
- Doing what? - Kinging.
- 忙什麼 - 做國王
Really?
是麼
Kinging.. is a precarious business these days!
現在國王…可沒那麼好當
Where is the Tsar of Russia?
俄國沙皇沒請？
Where is Cousin Wilhelm?
威廉表親也沒來？
You¡¯re being dreary.
別沒事找事
Is Kinging laying off eighty staff and buying yet more pearls for Wallis
國王的本職就是先辭掉80個家僕 再送華莉絲更多珍珠？
while there are people marching across Europe singing ¡°The Red Flag¡±?
現在歐洲可是有群眾遊行，唱著「紅旗飄揚」
Stop your worrying. Herr Hitler will sort that lot out.
別擔心了，希特勒肯定會擺平他們
Who¡¯ll sort out Herr Hitler?
那誰來擺平希特勒？
Where¡¯s the bloody 23¡¯?
那瓶23年的酒呢？
And you¡¯ve put that woman into our mother¡¯s suite?
你居然讓她住母親的房間？
Mother¡¯s not still in the bed, is she?
媽媽現在又沒睡覺
That¡¯s not funny.
這一點都不好笑
Here it is, Wally likes the very best.
找到了，華莉絲喜歡好酒
I don¡¯t care what woman you carry on with at night,
我不管你今晚和誰瀟灑
as long as you show up for duty in the morning!
只要你早上能履行職責！
Wallis is not just some woman I am carrying on with.
華莉絲不是我只想瀟灑一下的對象
We intend to marry
我們想要結婚
Excuse me?
什麼？
She¡¯s filing a petition for divorce.
她正在辦離婚
Good God.
我的天哪
Can¡¯t you just give her a nice house and a title?
你送她套房子和名頭不就行了？
I¡¯m not having her as my mistress.
我不想讓她當我的情婦
The Church does not recognise divorce
教會是不會承認離婚的
and you are the¡­ head of the Church.
你還…代表著教會
- Haven¡¯t I any rights? - Many privileges...
- 我沒有特權嗎？ - 很多優待條件
Not the same thing. Your beloved Common Man may marry for love,
這不一樣。你的百姓可以為了愛情結婚
Why not me?
我就不行？
If you were the Common Man,
如果想當百姓
on what basis could you possibly claim to be King?!
你做國王的依據又在哪堙H
Sounds like you¡¯ve studied our wretched constitution.
聽起來你對可悲的憲法研究很透啊
Sounds like you haven¡¯t.
聽起來你就沒讀過
Is that what this is all about? Bashing up?
原來你是這意思？推我下台？
Hence the elocution lessons?
背地媟d什麼辯論訓練
That¡¯s the scoop around town.
傳的滿城風雨了
I¡¯m trying to¡­to...
我只是…是想…
Yearning for a larger audience are we,
想要更多人聽你的話嗎
B-b-b-bertie?
伯伯伯…伯蒂？
D-don¡¯t¡­
別…別…
What¡¯s that? I¡¯m sorry.
什麼？沒聽懂啊
Young brother trying to push older brother off throne...
弟弟想要推翻哥哥的王位
Po..Po..sitively medieval.
相當有中…中世紀風格啊
- Wallis - where have you been all this time?
- 華莉絲 - 你剛才去哪兒了？
I¡¯ve been talking to.
有人找我聊天
Never mind.
算了
- It¡¯s very complicated little king you¡¯re  - I tried to be
- 你這國王還真是神秘莫測 - 努力保持風格
All that work, down the drain.
努力了半天都白費了
My own ..brother... I couldn¡¯t say.. a single word to him in reply!
我對…哥哥…當面說不出…一個字來！
Why do you stammer more with David than you do with me?
為什麼你對大衛結巴，對我說就沒事？
Because you¡¯re bloody well paid to listen!
那是因為我給你錢了！
Bertie I¡¯m not a geisha girl.
伯蒂，我可不是賣藝的歌女
Stop trying to be so bloody clever!
你就不能裝傻一下嗎！
What is it about David that stops you speaking?
究竟大衛哪一點讓你說不出話來？
What is it about you that bloody well make you want to go on about it the whole bloody time?
你怎麼老是對這爛事兒糾纏不休？
Vulgar but fluent. You don¡¯t stammer when you swear.
說粗話很流利，這時候你不結巴
Bugger off!
滾開！
Is that the best you can do?
罵人只能到這種程度？
Well bloody bugger to you, you beastly bastard.
你這討厭的傢伙，野蠻的混蛋
A public school prig can do better than that.
小學生都比你罵得狠
Shit. Shit, shit, shit!
媽的，媽的，媽的，媽的！
Defecation flows trippingly from the tongue?
嘴埵R髒字很輕鬆吧？
Because I¡¯m angry!
因為我很生氣！
Ah. Know the f-word?
噢，你知道F開頭的詞？
Fornication?
F..Fornication(通姦)？
Oh Bertie.
別裝了
Fuck. Fuck, fucking, fuck!
(Fuck)操，操，操，操！
Bugger, bugger, bugger!
混蛋，混蛋，混蛋！
Fuck Fuck ass
操操操，賤貨
- Balls Balls Fuckity - Yes! You see! Not a hesitation!
- 操蛋，操蛋 - 看到了吧，一點不結巴
Willy, Shit and Fuck, and tits
小雞雞，媽的，操，大波波
Dad? What¡¯s going on?
爸爸？你們在幹啥？
Sorry. Just finish your homework.
抱歉了，你繼續安心寫作業
Well that¡¯s a side of you we don¡¯t get to see all that often.
你的這種形象，人們可不常見到啊
No. No we¡¯re not supposed to really, not publicly.
有規矩的…至少公開場合不行
Let¡¯s get some air.
出去透透氣吧
No Logue, I don¡¯t think that¡¯s a good idea.
羅格，我覺得這麼出去不太好
What¡¯s the matter? Why are you so upset?
怎麼了？在擔心什麼事嗎？
Logue, you have no idea.
羅格，你想都想不到
My brother.. is infatuated with a woman who¡¯s been married twice
我哥哥…迷上了一個結了兩次婚的女人
She¡¯s asking for a divorce
她正在辦理離婚
And he is determined to marry her.
我哥鐵了心要娶她
Mrs Wallis Simpson of Baltimore.
來自巴爾的摩的華莉絲·辛普森夫人 （美國城市名）
That¡¯s not right. Queen Wallis of Baltimore?
聽著就不對勁。來自美國的英國王后？
Unthinkable.
成何體統
- Can he do it? - Absolutely not.
- 他能這麼做嗎？ - 絕對不行
But he¡¯s going to anyway. All hell¡¯s broken loose.
不過，他是收不住了，馬上事情就會一團糟
Can¡¯t they carry on privately?
他們就不能私下繼續嗎？
If only they would.
要是他們願意就好了
Where does that leave you?
這不是留給你位子了？
I know my place!
我知道我的位置！
I¡¯ll¡­ do anything within my power to keep my brother on the throne.
我…會盡一切所能，幫我哥哥保住王位
Is it that serious? Your place may be on the throne.
這不是很現實的情況嗎？你很可能當上國王
I am not an alternative to my brother.
我無意頂替我哥哥
- You can outshine David... - Don¡¯t take liberties!
- 你會比他更稱職 - 說話別太過分
That¡¯s bordering on treason.
你這算謀反
I¡¯m just saying you could be King. You could do it!
我只是說你能做個好國王，沒問題的
That is treason!
這是謀反！
I¡¯m trying to get you to realize you need not be governed by fear.
我只想讓你明白，你沒必要被恐懼束縛手腳
I¡¯ve had enough of this!
我受夠了！
What¡¯re you afraid of?
你在怕什麼？
Your poisonous words!
你惡毒的蠱惑！
Why¡¯d you come to me?
那你還來找我？
You¡¯re not middle-class banker who want elocution lessons¡­
你可不是什麼中產階級的銀行家，練練嘴皮子
- so you can chit-chat at posh tea parties? - Don¡¯t attempt to instruct me on my duties!
- 好在宴會上顯擺一下 - 別插手我的公事！
I¡¯m the son of a¡­ King...
我的父親是…國王
the brother of a King...
我的哥哥是…國王
You¡¯re the disappointing son of a brewer!
而你是個讓人失望的釀酒師的兒子
A jumped-up jackeroo from the outback!
鄉下過來的新手，亂給我指揮
You¡¯re nobody. These sessions are over!
你是無名小卒。治療結束！
Through here sir.
您這邊請
Garden Entrance.Prime Minister's Office.10 Dawning Street
花園入口，首相辦公室，唐寧街10號
It¡¯s not just because she¡¯s an American.
不單單因為她是美國人
That the least of it, it¡¯s because she is soon to be a twice divorced American,
雖然這點就足夠了，還因為她就要離婚兩次了
and the King, as the head of Church of England¡­
國王是英格蘭教會的領袖
can not marry a divorced woman.
不能娶一個離過婚的女人
And sir, I apologize for the nature of this, but...
殿下，這麼說可能有點過火…
according to Scotland Yard,
不過根據蘇格蘭場的調查
the King has not always possess exclusive rights to Mrs.Simpson¡¯s favours and affections,
辛普森太太愛的不止國王一個
sharing them with a married used car salesman,
現在還有個已婚的賣汽車的
a certain Mr Guy Trundle.
她是腳踩兩條船
In addition, it is also rumored that Hitler¡¯s ambassador,
另外，傳言希特勒的大使…
Count von Ribbentrop, sends her 17 carnations every day......
婸垢S洛甫，每天給她送17支康乃馨
Should His Majesty continue to ignore the advice of His Government,
如果國王陛下繼續無視內閣的忠告
He must abdicate. Otherwise His Government has no choice but to resign.
要麼他自己退位，要麼政府集體辭職
Prime Minister, you¡¯d leave the country without a¡­ government?
首相，在這個時候把國家變成一團散沙？
Does the King do what he wants,
究竟國王是自己隨心所欲…
or does he do what his people expect him to do?
還是承擔民眾賦予的職責？
As crowds on Donning Street watch Ministers come and go
唐寧街上的人們看著首相換了一屆又一屆
There raised an age-old problem.
還是繞不開一個老難題
Can the King separate his personal life from his public duty?
國王能否避免私生活影響自己的職責？
- What¡¯s the matter, love? - I¡¯m just having trouble with a patient
- 怎麼了，愛人？ - 有個病人很讓我操心
- it isn¡¯t like you. Why - He¡¯s scared.
- 這可不像你，怎麼回事 - 他很害怕
Frightened of his own shadow.
不相信自己的力量
Isn¡¯t that why they come to you?
所以才找你治療啊
This fellow could really be somebody great. He¡¯s fighting me.
這人可以真正成就一番事業 可他把功夫都花到和我作對上了
Perhaps he doesn¡¯t want to be great.
可能他只想過平常人的生活
Perhaps that¡¯s what you want.
是你把想法強加給他
I might have overstepped the mark.
我說的確實有點過分了…
Apologize. Deep of good.
那就道歉，真誠的道歉
I'm very sorry, Mr Logue,the Duke is busy
很抱歉，羅格先生，公爵現在很忙
I¡¯m happy to wait. Or I could come back later.
我能等他，或者我回頭再來
As I said, the Duke is terribly busy.
我告訴過您，公爵非常忙
Thank you
麻煩了
Parliament will not support the marriage.
議會不會支持這樁婚姻
But there were other reasons for concern.
不過反對聲音也有其他的考慮
He was careless with state papers.
國王這麼不懂法規
He lacked commitment and resolve.
這麼沒有決斷和獻身精神
There were those that worried where he would stand when war with Germany.
會有人擔心，當和德國開戰的時候 他能否頂住壓力
We¡¯re not coming to that?
會開戰嗎？
Indeed we are, Sir. Prime Minister Baldwin may deny this,
確實如此。雖然鮑德溫首相可能不承認
but Hitler¡¯s intent is crystal clear.
不過希特勒的野心昭然若揭
War with Germany will come,
和德國開戰勢在必然
and we will need a King we can all stand behind united.
我們需要一個強有力的國王代表我們的心聲
I fear..my brother is of sound mind at this time
我擔心…我哥哥現在的精神狀態不怎麼樣
Have you thought what you will call yourself?
就沒想過由你來承擔嗎？
I¡­I¡­
我…我…
Certainly not Albert, Sir. Too Germanic.
您當然不會，德國人才這麼熱衷權力
What about George? After your father?
那麼想想你哥哥？在你父親死後？
George the sixth.
新國王喬治六世
It has rather a nice continuity to it, don¡¯t you think.
他可是完美繼承了父親的品性啊，不是麼
David! Thank God. You look exhausted!
大衛！總算找到你了，你看起來精神很不好
How are you bearing up?
打起精神來啊
Bertie. The decision¡¯s been made. I¡¯m¡­ I¡¯m going
伯蒂，我已經決定了，我離開
I cannot accept that. You are in no condition to make that decision.
我不接受，你這麼做太不負責任了
I¡¯m afraid there¡¯s no other way.
我很抱歉，沒有其他的方案了
I must marry her.
我一定要娶她
My mind¡¯s made up. I¡¯m... sorry.
我決心已定。我…很抱歉
That¡¯s a terrible thing to hear.
這可不是好消息
nobody wants that. I least of all.
對誰來說都不是。尤其對我
At long last I am able to say a few words of my own.
我總算能說出我自己的心聲了 （我於1936年12月10日簽字證明）
I have never wanted to withhold anything
我其實一直不想隱瞞什麼 （愛德華簽署於觀景台城堡）
But until now, it has not been constitutionally possible for me to speak.
直到現在，按照法規，我才能說出想法
A few hours ago I discharged my last duty as King and Emperor.
幾個小時以前，我主動解除了國王的職責
Now that I have been succeeded by my brother, the Duke of York
現在由我的弟弟，約克公爵繼位
my first words must be to declare my allegiance to him.
我在這堙A首先表達對他的忠誠
This I do with all my heart.
全心全意地效忠於他
You all know the reasons which have impelled me to renounce the throne.
你們也知道我不能參加新王加冕的原因
But you must believe me when I tell you
不過，請你們相信
That I have found it impossible to carry the heavy burden of responsibility
如果沒有我心愛的女人支持
and to discharge my duties as King as I would wish to do
我無法承擔國王的重任
without the help and support of the woman I love...
也更不會有勇氣卸任王位
And I want you to know, this decision has been made less difficult to me
同樣，因為我對我弟弟十分瞭解
by the sure knowledge that my brother,
使我卸任時，能夠寬慰一些
with his long training in the public affairs of this country...
他對國家公事十分熟悉
...and with his fine qualities...
加上他的優秀品質
...will be able to take my place forthwith without interruption
不會讓國家接下來出現動盪
or injury to the life and progress of the empire.
或者阻礙大英帝國的發展
Accession Council.St James's Palace.12th Dec,1936
登基會議，1936年12月12日，聖詹姆斯宮
I meet you today.. in..
我今天與你們相見…在…
in circumstances which are ..
…在這樣的情況下…下…
I¡¯m sure you¡¯ll love it.
你們肯定會喜歡的
Thank you darling, saddles, Margret
謝謝，瑪格麗特，裝好馬鞍
Yes mom.
好的
Good boy.
很聽話嘛
- Mama, here¡¯s the Wilson saddle - thank you
- 媽媽，這是威爾遜馬鞍 - 謝謝
Don¡¯t worry, we¡¯ll get you food in a minute
別擔心，一會就餵你吃飯
Mama, will we have space for our horses in our new home?
媽媽，新家媟|有地方放小馬嗎？
Of course we will, darling, we¡¯ll have a palace of rooms.
當然，寶貝們，整個宮殿有的是房間
Curtsey.
屈膝禮
Your Majesty.
陛下
How was it?
講話如何？
I¡¯m trying to¡­ familiarise myself with what a state paper looks like.
我試著…熟悉一下公務文件
A despatch from Mr Baldwin which I don¡¯t understand a word of.
鮑德溫的急件我一個字都看不懂
David¡¯s finances.
這是哥哥的財務情況…
The Christmas broadcast ¨C
這是聖誕講話
I think that might be a mistake.
我覺得還會搞砸
Don¡¯t worry about that
別擔心了
Plans for the Coronation. I think that¡¯s an even bigger mistake.
還有加冕禮。我覺得到時候會更出醜
I¡¯m not a King.
我不是當國王的料
I¡¯m a naval officer. That¡¯s all I know
我只是個前海軍軍官，我就這水平
I¡¯m not a King, not a king.
我不是當國王的料，我配不上
- I¡¯m sorry. I¡¯m sorry. - No. Dear.
- 我很抱歉，我很抱歉 - 別這樣，親愛的
Dear, dear man...
我親愛的
I¡¯m sorry.
我很抱歉
You know, I refused your first two marriage proposals,
其實我兩次拒絕你的求婚
Not because I didn¡¯t love you,
不是因為我不愛你
but because I couldn¡¯t bear the idea of a royal life
而是因為我受不了王室的生活
Could bear the idea of a life of tours and public duties,
四處出訪，還有公眾責任
a life that no longer was really to be my own.
我不可能再安心過自己的小日子
Then I thought...he stammers so beautifully...
不過後來我想，他結巴的這麼可愛
they¡¯ll leave us alone.
大家會放過他的
STAND BY THE KING.GOD SAVE THE KING
（支持國王。上帝保佑他）
Waiting for a king to apologize,
等待國王的道歉
one can wait rather a long wait.
可要耐心等上很久
I¡¯m afraid we¡¯re slightly late.
恐怕我們遲到了一會
- This is home. Myrtle¡¯s at bridge.
這是我家了，我妻子去了倫敦橋
I¡¯ve made sure the boys are out.
我也讓孩子們出去了
It¡¯s lovely. Absolutely lovely.
很溫馨嘛，非常溫馨
- May I sit down? - Yes, of course
- 我能坐下嗎 - 當然
Would you like some tea, Ma¡¯am?
需要茶水嗎，夫人？
Yes. I¡¯ll help myself.
我自己來吧
Off you go now. Or must I knock your heads together?
你們忙吧，難道還要我把你倆綁到一起不成？
Here¡¯s your shilling
這是你贏的賭注
I.. understand what you were trying to say, Logue.
我…我明白你之前的意思了，羅格
I went about it the wrong way. I¡¯m sorry.
是我表達方式不對，很抱歉
So here I am.
我還是回來了
Is the nation ready for two minutes of radio silence?
希望這個國家準備好聽我兩分鐘的靜音廣播了
Every stammer always fears they will fall back to square one.
每個病人都害怕努力半天又回到起點
I don¡¯t let that happen.
我絕不會讓這種情況出現
If I fail in my duty... David could come back.
如果我沒能履行職責…大衛還能回來接任
I¡¯ve seen the placards
我看了佈告了
¡°God Save Our¡­ King!¡±
「上帝保佑我們…國王」
They don¡¯t mean me.
他們指的不是我
Every other monarch in history succeeded someone who was dead,
歷史上君主的繼任，都是在前人過世的情況下
Or about to be.
或者將不久於人世
My predecessor is not only alive, but very much so.
我的前任現在不僅活著，還活得好好的
Bloody mess! I can¡¯t even give them a Christmas Speech.
真是一團糟！我連聖誕講話都做不了
- Like your Dad used to do? - Precisely.
- 像你爸爸那樣？ - 是啊
He¡¯s not here anymore.
他已經不在了
Yes he is. He¡¯s on that shilling I gave you.
他還在，就在我給你的硬幣上面
Easy enough to give away.
放手…其實很容易
You don¡¯t have to carry him around in your pocket.
你不需要心婺佽菑鷟邞獐v子
Or your brother.
或者你哥哥
You don¡¯t need to be afraid of things you were afraid of when you were five.
五歲時能夠嚇到你的事情已經過去了
You¡¯re very much your own man, Bertie.
你現在已經完全自己做主了，伯蒂
Right
明白
Your face is next, mate.
以後硬幣上就是你的肖像了，老兄
Lionel? Dear?
萊諾？親愛的？
Myrtle!
我妻子！
- Is this your wife? - Yes.
- 她回來了？ - 是的
Bertie, come here
伯蒂，你過來
- Are you alright, Logue? - Yes.
- 羅格，你沒事兒吧 - 沒事兒
Shall we go through?
不該出去見面嗎？
Trust me it¡¯s important.
相信我，這麼做才行
What is it?
怎麼回事？
Your... your...
你……您……
It¡¯s ¡°Your Majesty¡±, the first time.
第一次叫陛下就好
After that, ¡°Ma¡¯am¡±, as in ham, not Ma¡¯lm as in palm.
然後可以稱呼「女士」，發音別發錯了
I haven¡¯t told her about us. Sit down, relax.
我沒和她說起過你們，先坐下歇歇
I¡¯m told your husband calls my husband Bertie
我聽說，你丈夫叫我丈夫「伯蒂」
and my husband calls your husband Lionel.
我丈夫叫你丈夫「萊諾」
I trust you won¡¯t call me Liz.
希望你不會叫我「莉絲」 （王后名字的昵稱）
Your Majesty, you may call me Mrs Logue, Ma¡¯am.
陛下，您可以稱呼我為羅格夫人
Very nice to meet you, Mrs Logue
見到你很高興，羅格夫人
- Logue, we can¡¯t stay here all day. - Yes we can.
- 羅格，咱們不能整天貓在這 - 必須這樣
- Logue.. - Look, I need to wait for the opportune moment.
- 羅格… - 我得等個恰當時機才行
- You¡¯re being a coward! - You¡¯re damn right.
- 你這是怕老婆 - 說的很對！
Get out there, man!
快出去，一家之主
Oh! Hello, Myrtle darling! You¡¯re early.
你好啊，親愛的老婆，你回來早了
I believe you two have met!
我相信你們已經見過面了
I don¡¯t believe you know....King George VI?
不過還沒見過…國王喬治六世吧？
It¡¯s very nice to meet you.
見到您很高興
Will their Majesties be staying to dinner?
陛下能一起吃晚飯嗎？
We would love to, such a treat, but alas...
我們很想，這麼盛情邀請，不過…
a previous engagement. What a pity.
我們之前有其他安排了，真是可惜
Archbishop.
大主教
Welcome your Majesty.
歡迎您，陛下
What a glorious transformation, Sir.
這塈鼣y的十分壯觀
I hope you¡¯ll forgive us if we continue our preparations.
希望我們繼續工作不會妨礙您
Now, allow me to guide you through the ceremony.
請允許我講一下儀式過程
We begin, of course at the West Door, then into the nave.
我們從西入口開始，然後到中間廣場
I see all your pronouncements are to be broadcast, Archbishop.
大主教，聽說你的所有宣言都會被廣播
Ah, yes, wireless is indeed a Pandora¡¯s Box.
是啊，無線電是把雙刃劍
I¡¯m afraid I¡¯ve also had to permit the newsreel cameras.
恐怕我也得批准新聞攝影機的拍攝
The product of which I shall personally edit.
回頭我會親自剪輯的
Without momentary hesitation.
肯定毫不猶豫
This is Dr. Logue from Harley Street.
這位是哈雷街的羅格醫生
He¡¯s¡­ my speech therapist.
他是我的語言矯正醫生
Your Grace
大人
Had I known Your Majesty was seeking assistance
要是我知道陛下需要協助
I would¡¯ve made my own recommendation.
我肯定會親自推薦人選
Dr. Logue will be attending the Coronation.
羅格醫生需要參加加冕禮
Well of course I shall speak to the Dean,
我當然可以和主持牧師說一下
but it will be extremely difficult.
不過可能會很難辦
I should like¡­ the Doctor to be seated in the¡­ King¡¯s Box.
我希望…醫生坐在…國王的包廂中
But members of your Family will be seated there, Sir.
可您的家人才能坐在那堙A陛下
That why it¡¯s suitable.
所以他正合適
And now, if you don¡¯t mind, your grace we need the premises.
現在，如果大人不介意的話 我們需要場地做一下排練
My dear fellow, this is Westminster Abbey!
這位先生，這堨i是威斯敏斯特教堂！
The Church must prepare his Majesty.
教會一定要為陛下做好準備
My preparations are equally important.
我的準備同樣重要
With complete privacy. If you don¡¯t mind.
需要無人打擾，希望您不要介意
Those are my wishes, Your Grace.
這也是我的意思，大人
I will place the Abbey at Your Majesty¡¯s disposal...this evening.
那今晚我把教堂給您處置
Your Majesty.
陛下
Look, he again. Come on.
看，他又來了。咱們走
I can¡¯t believe I¡¯m walking on Chaucer and Handel and Dickens.
真不敢相信我走在喬叟、亨德爾、狄更斯的墓上 （這些詩人葬在教堂的詩人角落堙^
Everything alright? Let¡¯s get cracking.
準備好了？開始吧
I'm not here to rehearse, "Doctor" Logue.
我來這兒不是綵排的，羅格「醫生」
Call me Lionel
叫我萊諾
True, you never¡­
是啊，你是一直…
called yourself 'Doctor'.I did that for you.
不叫自己醫生，是我自己這麼稱呼的
no training, no diploma, no.. qualifications.
沒有訓練，沒有文憑，沒有…執照
Just a great deal of nerve.
窮有一身的膽量
the star chamber inquisition, is it?
你這是來秘密審問我嘍？
You asked for trust and.. total equality.
你還希望能信任你，公平對待你
Bertie, I heard you at Wembley,
伯蒂，我聽了你在溫布利的講話
I was there.
我在場
My son Laurie said ¡°Do you think you could help that poor man?¡±
我兒子勞婸﹛u你不能想法幫幫這個可憐人」？
What, as a failed actor!?
就憑一個失業演員？
It¡¯s true, I¡¯m not a doctor, and yes I acted a bit,
我確實不是醫生，我也曾經參加表演
I recited in pubs and taught elocution in schools.
我以前在酒吧朗誦，在學校教書
When the Great War came, our soldiers were pouring back from the front,
戰爭來臨時，大量前線士兵因為驚嚇…
shell-shocked and unable to speak
…回到後方了，就不再開口說話
and somebody said,"Lionel, you're very good at all this speech stuff.
有人說，「萊諾，你不是對語言挺在行麼」
Do you think you could possibly help these poor buggers¡±.
「你能想法幫幫他們嗎」
I did muscle therapy, exercise, relaxation,
我嘗試了肌肉治療、練習、放鬆
but I knew I had to go deeper.
不過我知道想根治還得更深入
Those poor young blokes had cried out in fear,
這些小伙子們因為恐懼哭出聲來
and no-one was listening to them.
卻沒有人去用心聽他們說話
My job was to give them faith in their voice
我的工作，是給他們說話的自信
and let them know that a friend was listening.
讓他們知道，總有位朋友願意傾聽
That must ring a few bells with you, Bertie.
這不是和你的治療很像嗎，伯蒂
You give a very noble account of yourself.
你這樣太拔高自己了
Make inquiries. It¡¯s all true.
你去問問，都是事實
Inquiries have been made!
我都問過了！
You have no idea who I have breathing down my neck.
你是不知道有多少人巴不得幫我打聽清楚
I vouched for you and you have no¡­credentials.
我為你做了擔保，你卻連證書…都沒有
But lots of success! I can¡¯t show you a certificate
可我治療成功了很多人！我沒有證書給你看
there was no training then.
那時也沒有系統的訓練機構
All I know I know by experience,
我只是按著經驗行事
and that war was some experience.
是這場戰爭，給了我經驗
May plaque says, ¡®L.Logue, Speech Defects¡¯.
我的牌子上寫的是「L 羅格 語言矯正」
No Dr., no letters after my name.
我沒有自稱醫生
Lock me in the Tower.
關我進監獄好了
I would if I could!
如果我有機會的話！
On what charge?
什麼罪名？
Fraud! With war looming,
詐騙！戰爭迫在眉睫
you¡¯ve saddle this nation with a voiceless King.
你讓這國家的國王不能說話
You destroyed the happiness of my family...
毀了我家庭的幸福
all for the sake of ensnaring a star patient
這都是精心誘捕一個知名病人的圈套
you couldn't possibly hope to assist!
你不可能治好！
It¡¯ll be like mad ¡­King George the Third,
我會像瘋國王喬治三世那樣…
there¡¯ll be¡­Mad King George the Stammerer,
留下個結巴國王喬治的名號
who let his people down so badly in their hour of need!
在這樣的關鍵時刻辜負人民的期望
What¡¯re you doing? Get up! You can¡¯t sit there! Get up
你這成何體統？起來！ 這不是你坐的！起來
Why not? It¡¯s a chair.
有什麼？不過是把椅子
No, it¡¯s not, that is¡­ Saint Edward¡¯s Chair-
這不是…這是…聖愛德華的椅子
People have carved their name into it!
人們還往上刻名字呢！
That chair is the seat on which every King and Queen
這椅子上坐過所有的國王和王后
It¡¯s held in place by a large rock!
不過是塊石頭上的椅子
That is the Stone of Scone,
這是命運之石
- you are trivialising everything - I don¡¯t care.
- 你怎麼藐視一切 - 我不在乎
I don¡¯t care how many Royal arses have sat in this chair-
我不在乎有多少王室成員的屁股坐過這
Listen to me... ! Listen to me... ! Listen to me... !
你聽我說！你聽我說！
- Listen to you?! By what right?
- 聽你的？為什麼
My divine right, if you must! I¡¯m your King!!!
我有權，你必須服從，我是國王！
Noooo you¡¯re not! Told me so yourself.
你才不是，親自跟我說…
Said you didn¡¯t want it. Why should I waste my time listening to you?
…你不想當。我幹嘛要聽你的？
Because I have a right to be heard!
因為我有發表意見的權利！
I HAVE A VOICE!!!
我的聲音有份量！
Yes you do.
是的，你有
You have such perseverance, Bertie,
伯蒂，你有毅力
you¡¯re the bravest man I know.
你是我認識的最勇敢的人
you¡¯ll make a bloody good king.
你會成為一個相當好的國王
What on earth¡¯s going on, Sir?
這究竟是怎麼回事，陛下？
It¡¯s quite all right, Archbishop.
大主教，沒事的
Mr Logue, you should know that I have found a replacement English specialist
羅格先生，我已經找到了一個治療師替換你
with impeccable credentials. Hence, your services will no longer be required.
簡歷無可挑剔。這堣]不再需要你的服務了
I¡¯m sorry?
怎麼回事？
Your Majesty¡¯s function is to consult and be advised.
國王可以詢問或者被告知結果
You didn¡¯t consult, but you¡¯ve just been advised.
您沒詢問過我，那我告訴您結果
Now I advise you: in this personal matter I will make my own decision.
那我告訴你：這件事上，我必須自己做主
My concern is for the head upon which I must place the crown.
我關心的是，王冠加冕在明君的頭上
I appreciate that Archbishop
我欣賞您的坦誠，大主教
but it¡¯s my head!
可這是我的頭
Your humble servant.
那卑職告退
Thank you Bertie.
謝謝，伯蒂
Shall we rehearse?
我們排練一下？
Come on, up on your perch
來吧，坐在你位置上
Now when you and Elizabeth enter through West door,
當你和王后進入西門
you¡¯ll be greeted with the hymn ¡°I Was Glad When They Said Unto Me.¡±
人們會唱讚歌迎接你們：「對我說，我就歡喜」
You won¡¯t actually be that glad,
不過你們歡喜不了
because they sing it for a great long time.
他們會唱上很久很久
Then your friend the Archbishop will ponce up the stairs towards you
然後你的朋友，主教大人會登上樓梯
and say, "Sir, is Your Majesty willing to take The Oath?"
對你說「陛下，您願意宣誓嗎？」
¡°I am willing¡±.
「我願意」
Course you are! I¡¯ll see what it sounds like from the cheap seats
你當然願意!我在後排聽聽效果如何
so even your old nanny can hear.
得讓你的老奶媽也聽得到
¡°Will you govern your peoples of Great Britain, Ireland,
「您願意統治大不列顛的領土…」
Canada, Australia and New Zealand according to their lands and customs?¡±
還包含愛爾蘭，加拿大，澳大利亞，新西蘭， 並尊重他們的土地和習俗嗎？」
"I solemnly promise so do so."
「我莊嚴起誓，我願意」
LOUDER! I can¡¯t hear you up the back.
大聲點！後面聽不到
¡°I SOLEMNLY PROMISE TO DO SO!¡±
「我莊嚴起誓，我願意！」
Very good! "Will you to your power cause Law and Justice,
非常好！「您願意在所有決定中…」
in Mercy, to be executed in all your judgments?"
「都考慮到法律、公平和仁慈嗎？」
"I will." ¡°I WILL!¡±
「我願意」，「我願意！」
Then a long bit about upholding the faith goes on, rubbish, rubbish
然後會有人們共同努力之類的話…等等
To which you finally say...
最後，你需要說…
¡°These things which I have here before promised,
「剛才我所承諾過的」
I will perform and keep. So help me God.¡±
「我會為之鞠躬盡瘁，請上帝保佑我」
That¡¯s all you have to say. Four short responses,
需要說的就這麼多，簡短四句話
kiss the book and sign the oath.
親吻法典，簽上誓言
There you are: you¡¯re King.
大功告成：你就是國王了
Easy.
很簡單
You nearly crowned him backwards Archbishop!
你差點把王冠帶反了，大主教
Someone had removed the thread marking the front of the Crown, Sir.
有人把王冠正面的線拆掉了，陛下
Try not lose the thread, Archbishop.
可別這樣了，大主教
Archbishop, your missing Papa.
大主教，你戴偏了王冠
Very good, very good. Archbishop.
非常好，非常好，大主教
Well, I hope Your Majesties are thrilled with the result.
我希望陛下對於結果很滿意
You can switch that machine off now.
你可以把機器關掉了
No, wait, keeping going.
不，等等，繼續放吧
Do have a seat, Archbishop.
主教請坐
(Hitler)
（希特勒）
Papa, what¡¯s he saying?
爸爸，他在說什麼？
I don¡¯t know, but he seems to be saying it rather well.
聽不懂，不過聽起來他說得很流利
Sir, I have asked to see you today in order to tender my resignation as Prime Minister.
陛下，我今天請求見您是要辭掉首相職務
I am so sorry to hear that, Mr Baldwin.
鮑德溫先生，我很遺憾
Neville Chamberlain will take my place as Prime Minister.
張伯倫會接替我的首相職務
It¡¯s a matter of principal. I was mistaken.
是原則問題，我之前的判斷失誤
I have found it impossible to believe that
我仍然難以相信…
there is any man in the World so lacking in moral feeling as Hitler,
世界上會有希特勒這樣沒有道德感的人
but the world might be hurled for a second time into the abyss of destructive War.
整個世界可能會捲進第二次戰爭的漩渦
Churchill was right all along. This was always Hitler¡¯s intention.
丘吉爾是對的，希特勒一直有這個野心
I am only sorry to leave you in this great time of crisis.
我只是覺得，在這樣的危機關頭辭職
I am very much afraid Sir,
我深感遺憾，我擔心
That your greatest test is yet to come.
對您的最大考驗，即將到來
I am speaking to you from the cabinet room of 10 Downing Street.(3rd,Sep,1939)
我是在唐寧街10號的內閣會議發來報道 （1939年9月3日）
This morning the British Ambassador in Berlin handed the German Government
今天早上，在柏林的英國大使 向德國政府發出最後通牒
a final note stating that unless we heard from them by 11 o¡¯clock
如果我們不在11點之前收到答覆
that they were prepared at once to withdraw their troops from Poland,
如果德國不立即從波蘭撤軍的話
a state of war would exist between us.
英國將對德國宣戰
I have to tell you now that no such undertaking has been received,
我們現在沒有接到德國的通知
and that consequently this country is at war with Germany.
這意味著英國對德國正式宣戰
At last. Sir, here¡¯s your speech. You are on air at six.
總算好了，這是您的演講，6點鐘直播
I¡¯ve timed it to just under nine minutes.
演講大概需要9分鐘
The wording is fully approved.
稿子已經經過了審核
The Prime Minister will be joining you for the broadcast
首相也會在廣播節目中和您一起出席
which will go out live across to the Nation,
講話會對整個大英帝國廣播
the Empire and to our Armed Forces.
我們的武裝部隊也能收到
Get Logue here immediately.
馬上請羅格過來
there are the barrage balloons.
吸引火力用的氣球
Yes, they got them up there quickly.
是啊，很快就升起來了
Should we pull over and find shelter?
我們要不停車躲一下？
No, go straight there. We'll be alright.
不，繼續往前開，別擔心
- Yes sir? - Lionel Logue, Major Harding is expecting me
- 您好 - 我是萊諾·羅格，哈丁少校找我
This is my son Laurie
這是我兒子勞
- Thank you Laurie  -Good luck dad
- 謝謝，勞 - 祝你好運，爸爸
- The King¡¯s speech, we have about 40 minutes to the broadcast - Thank you
- 國王的演講，還有40分鐘的時間 - 謝謝
Thank you very much. Thank you
非常感謝，謝謝
"There may be dark days ahead,and..."
「黑暗的日子即將來臨…」
Try again.
再來
¡°There may be dark days ahead, andw-... ¡±
「黑暗的日子即將來臨，戰…」
Turn the hesitations into pauses, and say to yourself,
把猶豫變成語氣停頓，心媕q念
¡°God save the King¡±.
「上帝保佑國王」
I say that continually, but apparently no one¡¯s listening.
我一直這麼說，看起來沒人聽啊
Long pauses are good: they add solemnity to great occasions.
長時間的停頓很不錯，在這樣的場合更顯得莊重
Then I¡¯m the solemnest king who ever lived.
那我就是歷史上最莊重的國王了
If I am a..King...where is my power?
如果我是…國王，那我有什麼權力？
Can I form a Government,
我能組建政府嗎？
Can I levy a tax or declare a war?
提高稅收，或者發動戰爭？
No! Yet I am the seat of all authority.
不行！可我還是要出面坐頭把交椅
Why? Because the Nation believes when I speak,
為什麼？因為整個國家相信…
I speak for them. Yet I cannot speak!
我的聲音代表著他們。可我說不出來！
Let's take it all again from the top. "In this grave hour..."
我們從頭再來一遍，「在這樣的嚴峻時刻」
¡°In this grave hour fuck fuck fuck
「在這樣的嚴峻時刻，操操操」
perhaps the most fateful in our
可能是歷史上最緊要的…
history bugger shit shit
…關頭，混蛋，媽的
I send to every household of my p-p-
我為每個家庭的人…
The ¡®P¡¯ is always difficult even when I¡¯m singing
我唱歌的時候都發不好P這個音
Bounce onto it 'a-peoples'
那就利用a的發音跳過去
¡°a-peoples both at home and overseas,...¡±
不論是國內還是海外…
Beautiful.
很不錯
¡°... this message, doo-dah, doodah....
「這消息，啦啦啦啦」
spoken with the same depth of feeling...doodah
我和你們一樣懷著深情…啦啦
for each one of you as if I able to fuck shit bugger
帶給我全部的子民們，操，媽的，混蛋
cross your threshold and speak to you m-my - ...¡±
跨過家家的門檻，帶來我的…
In your head, now: ¡°I have a right to be bloody well heard!¡±
腦子現在想：「我有發言權」
Bloody well heard, bloody well heard,
發什麼言，發什麼言
bloody well heard myself!
除了我自己誰在聽
Now Waltz. Move! Get continuous movement.
現在是華爾茲舞，動起來，連續運動
¡°For the second time in the lives of most of us we are at wa - ...¡±
「這是我們大部分人第二次…」
Pause. ¡°we are...¡± Take a pause.
暫停…「我們…」再暫停
I can¡¯t do this.
這我做不成
Bertie, you can do it. Have a look at the last paragraph.
伯蒂，你能行的，看看最後一個自然段
Bertie...it¡¯s time.
伯蒂，時間到了
- Archbishop - Your Majesty
- 大主教 - 陛下
A great moment, sir.
載入歷史的時刻，陛下
- Prime Minister. - Your Majesty
- 首相 - 陛下
Nice to see you again, so soon.
很高興能這麼快再次見面
Good.. of you to be here, I¡¯m sure you¡¯ve had rather a busy day.
你能來…很好。相信你們今天都很忙
Let¡¯s hope we have no more interruptions from those damned sirens, Sir.
希望我們不會受到空襲警報的影響
Or the wretched dogs.
或者這些可憐的小狗
- Congratulations. First Lord of the Admiralty. - Your Majesty.
- 恭喜，新任海軍大臣 - 陛下
The long walk.
還得走上一段路
Good luck, Sir. I too dread this...apparatus.
祝您好運。我也擔心過發音問題
Had a speech impediment myself, you know.
我也結巴
- I didn¡¯t. - Family secret. Tongue-tied.
- 這我可真不知道 - 家族秘密了，說話結巴
An operation was considered too dangerous.
做手術的話風險太大
I eventually made an asset of it.
最後終於把這種嗓音變成我的個人特色
- Thank you, Mr Churchill. - Sir.
- 謝謝，丘吉爾先生 - 陛下
Darling
親愛的
How long, Logue?
還需要多久？
Just under three minutes, Sir.
還要3分鐘
(5,4,3,check,2,1)
（5，4，3試音，2，1）
Mr Wood.
伍德先生
Good luck, Your Majesty.
祝您好運，陛下
- You¡¯ve redecorated, Logue. - I made it cozy.
- 你重新佈置了這堙A羅格 - 讓環境舒服些
Some fresh air.
來點新鮮空氣
There you are, darling.
好了，親愛的
I am thistle sifter, I have a sieve of sifted thistles
我篩選薊草,我有個篩好薊草的篩子 （繞口令）
and a sieve on unsifted thistles..
我有個沒篩好薊草的篩子
Bertie, darling, make sure it¡¯s not switched on!
伯蒂，寶貝，確定麥克風沒開吧
Remember the red light will blink four times and then I¡¯ve asked them to turn it off,
記住，紅燈閃爍4下之後，我會讓人滅掉燈
because we don¡¯t want that evil eye staring at you all the way through.
免得有個鬼眼似的東西老盯著你
One minute, sir.
還有1分鐘
I am sure you will be splendid.
肯定會有出色的表現
40 second, sir
還有40秒
Logue, however this turns out,
羅格，不管演講結果怎樣
I don¡¯t know how to thank you for what you¡¯ve done.
我都不知道該怎麼回報你的幫助
Knighthood?
獎個爵位？
Twenty seconds.
20秒
Forget everything else and just say it to me.
排除雜念，只想著說給我聽
Say it to me, as a friend.
說給我這個朋友聽
In this grave hour, perhaps the most fateful in our history,
在這樣嚴峻的時刻，可能是國家存亡的緊要關頭
I send to every household of my peoples,
我向領土上的所有子民
both at home and overseas
不論是國內或是海外
this message
傳達這份消息
spoken with the same depth of feeling for each one of you
我和你們一樣，百感交集
as if I were able to cross your threshold and speak to you myself.
只希望我能挨家挨戶親自向你們訴說
For the second time in the lives of most of us we are at war.
我們大部分人，都是第二次經歷戰爭的洗禮
Over and over again we have tried to find a peaceful way out
不止一次，我們嘗試過尋求和平之道
of the differences between ourselves and those who are now our enemies.
求同存異，化敵為友
But it has been in vain. We have been forced into a conflict.
然而徒勞無功。我們被迫捲入了一場戰爭
For we are called, to meet the challenge of a principle which,
我們所面臨的，是一個邪惡信念的挑戰
if it were to prevail, would be fatal to any civilized order in the world.
如果敵方取勝，世界的文明秩序將毀於一旦
Such a principle, stripped of all disguise,
這樣的信念，剝去偽裝的外衣
is surely the mere primitive doctrine that might is right.
只是赤裸裸的權力追求
For the sake of all that we ourselves hold dear,
為了捍衛凝聚起我們的所有
it is unthinkable that we should refuse to meet the challenge.
我們無法想像去逃避這樣的挑戰
It is to this high purpose that I now call my people at home
為了如此崇高目標，我呼籲國內的民眾
and my peoples across the seas, who will make our cause their own.
海外的子民們，萬眾一心
I ask them to stand calm and firm, and united in this time of trial.
我希望你們能冷靜堅定，在時間的歷練中團結向前
The task will be hard. There may be dark days ahead,
任務將會困難重重，前路可能烏雲密佈
and war can no longer be confined to the battlefield.
戰場將不再局限於前線陣地。
But we can only do the right as we see the right
只有掌握真知才能正確行事
and reverently commit our cause to God.
在此我們虔誠的向上帝承諾
If one and all we keep resolutely faithful to it,
如果我們大家堅定信念
then, with God¡¯s help, we shall prevail.
上帝會保佑，我們必將獲勝
That was very good, Bertie.
說的非常棒，伯蒂
You still stammered on the ¡°w¡±.
不過發w這音還是會結巴
Had to throw in a few so they knew it was me.
不能太流利了，免得懷疑是替身
Congratulations, your Majesty. A true broadcaster.
祝賀您，陛下，專業的播音員水準
Thank you, Mr Wood.
謝謝，伍德先生
Congratulations, your Majesty.
恭喜陛下
Thank you.
謝謝
- Ready? - Good
- 準備？ - 好
Perfect
非常好
Your first war time speech. Congratulation.
你的第一次戰時演講，祝賀你
Expect I shall have to do a great deal more.
以後的演講少不了
Thank you, Logue.
謝謝，羅格
Well done. My friend.
做得好，我的老兄
Thank you... Your Majesty.
謝謝您，陛下
I knew you¡¯d be good.
我就知道你沒問題
Thank you...
謝謝你…
...Lionel. (first time call Lionel)
萊諾
Onwards?
去陽台？
Congratulations, Sir
恭喜陛下
Couldn¡¯t have said it better myself, Sir
我自嘆不如
Your Majesty, I¡¯m speechless.
陛下，您讓我啞口無言
Congratulations, Sir
祝賀您，陛下
Gentlemen.
先生們
So how was Papa, Elizabeth?
爸爸表現如何，伊麗莎白？
Halting at first, but you got much better Papa.
開頭停了會，不過後面好的多
Bless you.
上帝保佑你
And how about you, Margret?
你覺得呢，瑪格麗特？
You were just splendid, Papa.
你很了不起，爸爸
Of course I was.
是很驚人
You¡¯re all ready?
你們都準備好了？
Come on girls.
過來吧，孩子們
King George VI made Lionel Logue
喬治六世在1944年
a Commander of the Royal Victorian Order in 1944.
授予萊諾 維多利亞三等勳章
This high honour from a grateful King made Lionel part of
這份國王的感恩之情也開創了先例
the only order of chivalry that specifically rewards acts of personal service to the Monarch.
這是唯一一枚為王室服務的特別騎士勳章
Lionel was with the King for every wartime speech.
國王在戰爭中的每次演講，都有萊諾陪在身邊
Through his broadcasts, George VI became a symbol of national resistance.
這些廣播，使喬治六世成為了英國抵抗精神的代言人
Lionel and Bertie remained friends for the rest of their lives.
萊諾和伯蒂在餘生中一直維持著親密的友誼
The End
謝謝觀賞 TLF中文字幕站 http://tlfsubs.eastgame.org